I added my rule here in the last lecture but it's missing a loader and for javascript I mentioned that I
Kuralm buraya son derste ekledim ama bir ykleyici eksik ve javascript iin javascriptimi
want to use babel, the defacto standard for transpiling my javascript. We will install it with npm install
aktarmak iin babel, defacto standardn kullanmak istediimi belirttim. Npm install --save-dev ile tekrar
--save-dev again because it's a development only dependency and we need to install the babel-loader
ykleyeceiz nk bu sadece bir bamllk gelimesi ve babel-loader
package,
paketini kurmamz gerekiyor,
that however does just provide the hook for webpack. Babel itself is a library which kind of has the knowledge
ancak sadece webpack iin kanca salyoruz. Babel'in kendisi, javascript'inizi nasl aktaracanz konusunda bir
about how to transpile your javascript,
bilgiye sahip olan bir ktphanedir.
so we also need to install babel-core which holds that knowledge.
Bu nedenle, bu bilgiyi tutan babil ekirdei de yklememiz gerekir.
We now also need some configurations to basically tell babel which kind of next generation javascript
imdi, babel'e yeni nesil javascript'in hangi trden javascript szdizimini desteklediimizi ve
or which special javascript syntax we want to support and here, these are so-called presets, the packages
burada szn ettiimiz ve burada szde n ayarlar olarak adlandrdmz baz konfigrasyonlara ihtiyacmz
we need are babel-preset-react to support jsx and babel-preset-env for an environment
var. htiya duyduumuz paketler, jsx ve babel'i desteklemek iin bab-preset-tepki Temel olarak, kullandmz zelliklere bir gz attmz ve otomatik
adjusting preset which basically has a look at the features we use and automatically transpiles everything
olarak her eyi doru bir ekilde aktaran bir ortam ayar hazrl iin
correctly.
-preset-env.
So these are the dependencies I'll install now,
Yani bunlar imdi kurduum bamllklar, imdi de projemizi
now we also need to configure our project, we need to configure babel first of all. So the installation
yaplandrmamz gerekiyor, her eyden nce babeyi yaplandrmamz gerekiyor. Bu yzden kurulum bitti, imdi babeyi yaplandrmamz
finished,
gerekiyor
now we need to configure babel because just because we installed the presets doesn't make babel use
nk sadece n ayarlarn yklenmesinden dolay babel kullanmyoruz, yklediimiz tm dier paketleri
them, it doesn't analyze all other packages we installed and then see if there is a preset inside of them.
analiz etmiyoruz ve daha sonra iinde bir n ayar olup olmadn gryoruz.
So instead we add a new file, dot and the dot at the beginning is important, .babelrc
Bunun yerine yeni bir dosya ekliyoruz, nokta ve balangtaki nokta nemlidir. babelrc.
that's a configuration file babel will automatically read if it's in our root folder,
Bu, babamzn kk klasrmzde otomatik olarak okuyaca bir yaplandrma dosyasdr. Bu
so in the same folder where we will later run our webpack build workflow. The babelrc file takes adjacent
nedenle, daha sonra web paketi oluturma i akmz yrteceimiz ayn klasrde. Babelrc dosyas bitiik bir konfigrasyon alr ve orada
configuration and there we should add a presets node,
bir n ayar dm eklemeliyiz, imdi babil'i uygulamak
now we can make babel aware of all the presets we want to apply and here, I want to apply two of the
istediimiz tm n ayarlardan haberdar edebiliriz ve burada iki n ayar
presets,
uygulamak
the first one is env and the second is react.
istiyorum, ilki env ve ikincisi tepki.
So these are the two presets we installed without the babel-preset- thing at the beginning,
Bu yzden balangta babel-preset-thing olmakszn kurduumuz iki n ayar,
just the path at the end so react and env, these are the two presets.
sadece sondaki tepki ve env yoludur, bunlar iki n ayardr.
Now the env preset will receive some special configuration from my side,
imdi env n ayarm benim tarafmdan baz zel konfigrasyonlar alacak,
I do this by enclosing it into an array with square brackets and then the second argument after the
bunu keli parantezler ieren bir diziye ekleyerek yapyorum ve n ayarn
name of the preset is a javascript object where I can configure it
adndan sonra ikinci argman yaplandrabileceim bir
and here I want to set up the targets of that preset
javascript nesnesi. Bu n ayarn hedeflerini kurmak,
which means which browser versions do I want to support,
hangi tarayc srmlerini desteklemek istiyorum, tabii
that's of course important.
ki nemli.
It automatically identifies which next generation features I use
Hangi yeni nesil zellikleri kullandigimi otomatik olarak tanimiyor, ancak
but to know what next generation actually means, it needs to know what my current gen is,
gelecek nesilin ne anlama geldiini bilmek, o anki genimin ne oldugunu bilmem
so which browsers do I target with my app?
gerekiyor, bu yzden hangi tarayicilari uygulamamla hedeflerim?
So targets is another javascript object where we can then set up browsers and browsers
Bu yzden hedefler, tarayclar ve tarayclar oluturabileceimiz baka bir javascript nesnesidir,
then is an array where we can use the browser list type of configuration,
ardndan tarayc listesi yaplandrma trn kullanabileceimiz bir dizidir, kullanabileceiniz szdizimi hakknda daha
you can google for browser list to find this repository here to learn more about the syntax you can
fazla bilgi edinmek iin bu depoyu bulmak iin tarayc listesi iin google'a bavurabilirsiniz.
use for configuring browsers.
tarayclar yaplandrmak iin.
However the syntax
Ancak size
I'll show you here is a pretty common set up.
burada gstereceim szdizimi olduka yaygn bir ayardr.
So what we want to do here is we want to target greater 1% of market share
yleyse burada yapmak istediimiz ey, pazar paynn ya da
or last two versions so this is will be combined with or in between.
son iki versiyonun% 1'ini hedeflemek istiyoruz, bylece bu ya da aralarnda bir araya getirilecek.
So now this is the target environment we want to support and this is what babel will then take into
imdi bu, desteklemeyi arzu ettiimiz hedef ortamdr ve bu, babil'in yeni nesil
account when compiling our next generation javascript to current gen,
javascript'i gncel genle derlerken hesaba katt eydir,
it will compile it to javascript which runs in browsers which fulfill this criteria.
bu, bu ltleri karlayan tarayclarda alan javascript ile derlenecektir.
So with that, we get the babel configuration finished,
Bylece, babel konfigrasyonunu tamamladk,
now we can add the babel loader in our webpack config, there I'll therefore add a loader in single
imdi babpack ykleyicimizi webpack konfigrasyonumuza ekleyebiliriz, o yzden orada bir ykleyiciyi tek trnak
quotation marks,
iaretleri olan
the babel-loader.
babel-loader'a ekleyeceim.
So here I take the full name of the package we installed, babel-loader.
Bu yzden, yklediimiz paketin adn, babel-loader' aldm.
So now it will be applied to javascript files compiling the jsx and next generation javascript features,
Yani imdi jsx ve yeni nesil javascript zellikleri derleme javascript dosyalar iin uygulanacaktr,
it would still fail though because we also import css which webpack wouldn't understand, it only understands
yine de webpack anlayamayaca css ithal nk yine de baarsz olurdu, sadece javascript anlyorum ve pizzaImage
javascript natively
bileeni, css
and in the pizzaImage component,
ithal olurdu ve hatta
it would import css and even an image,
bir grnt, bu yzden bunu da
so we need to support that too.
desteklememiz gerekiyor.
Let's add support for these types of files in the next lecture.
Bir sonraki derste bu tr dosyalar iin destek ekleyelim.